OK.
One second, I'll.
I may need to.
Open the eye.
Oh.
OK, so second day,
second round of exercises. OK,
so on Monday we.
Finished. Um.
A number of we finished the example of
generating some code and.
How we can use the AI for that purpose.
Now today I'd like to explore with you
some code base.
As an example.
Of um.
Learning.
So anyone has any preferences?
Of course,
it should be available on GitHub,
of course.
And top.
Is that OK?
OK,
today let's try to be more interactive.
So I will.
Stop.org.
Which one? The original and top?
Uh, it can be done. OK.
Com.
OK, blackboard and chalk.
Come on, too many requests.
You have exceeded a secondary rate limit.
One way too many request.
Let me sign in.
Let's use the.
I move my lap.
Yeah.
Vitab.
Back.
OK.
M Top Eng.
OK.
Perfect.
Now.
So in general,
I don't think the assignment will be tell
me something about and top.
I mean it will be something more like how
these things.
Is implemented or work or can be done or
is the code efficiency efficient or we
can improve some areas or I don't know,
I mean perform some security.
Checks looking for potential
vulnerabilities into the code base. OK,
so so I mean particular preference for
this code base and top for those of you
that are not familiar with it's.
An open source system maintained by
Professor Derry that you may know it's
around networking and so I mean questions
and analysis will be.
Likely to be in in this space. OK, so.
Goal. Any preferences?
Mm-hmm.
I mean if this was supposed to be a
project for the course,
which is explore and top Ng codebase 4.
Or what? I mean it it it will not be,
it will never be explore this code base.
I mean it's rather pointless.
It's complicated.
You have to set up your goals.
So I mean let's define a clear goal of
the project. So the project is.
What we are looking uh into this code
base?
Efficiency of the code I will. I mean,
let's let's say I would rather prefer
security.
Because the efficiency of the code
requires,
I will probably never ask for that. OK,
because it's first it's more about
algorithms. Second,
you probably need some more licenses to
because the overall efficiency.
Of a code base,
unless it's a system in a single file or
in few files.
Otherwise it's impossible for you to
provide the full set of files to expect
for efficiency. So I mean.
It will be tricky to to to perform this
kind of analysis using the eye,
so I will always look for analysis that
are suitable that you can do reasonably
well by copy pasting,
downloading code bases, etcetera,
but without having to to.
To look too many files at once.
So I mean it's.
Let's say let's look for.
So uh.
You can when you explore a code base,
in this case on top is written in C++,
let's say C++ will be the core.
OK.
So uh.
Question that I may ask around the C++
codebase can be around the memory
management style of the codebase and
whether.
There are dangerous patterns for dynamic
references or use and abuse of pointers
that may, you know,
compromise the security of the
application or these kind of things. OK,
so let let's stick.
The space of in the space of pointers,
memory management and security related
properties.
And let's assume that the goal was set
like this.
I mean explore the top Ng project.
Looking for the convention used in the
C++ project for managing the memory and
spot potential.
So find the the style of memory
management and look for potential issues
in in in this both in security and in
performance.
It will be already complicated as a as a
task. OK, in general,
whether we ask it or not,
if you decide to go for a code
exploration.
Include a brief out outline of the style
and the conventions that are used in the
in the code base. And by the way,
of course we are focusing on the AI,
but it's not forbidden to do traditional
stuff. OK, I mean.
But the the fact that we say to use AI
doesn't mean that you can't use Visual
Studio or Code or any editor,
read the code by your own, etcetera.
I mean it's basically the AI.
Will help you to make tractable tractable
the problem because if you have to read
and learn the the code base,
a complex code base is basically
impossible in 10 days with DI becomes
possible. OK so.
So I I don't want you to think that the
assignment is just typing in the AI.
I mean it can be a mixed.
It can also be a different interaction
with the AI because for instance on
GitHub you also have copilot.
8.
You take a pilot which is included with
some limits in the in the free version
and you can use that instead of.
Use downloading the source code and
passing the source code to some other AI.
So basically in this respect,
find your own balance and I mean there is
no particular prescriptions in how to do
this thing, OK.
O.
What you will do now that we set up our
goal?
In the meantime, I try to.
Understand whether.
I can.
Oh, now looks more like it should.
There we are, OK.
Be much better.
Uh.
So, how would you proceed?
I would use the gravity to analyze the
code base and make me a brief how it's
structured the technologies anti gravity.
Uh.
A good AI integrated the ID.
I'm available for download.
OK, free.
Hit a stop.
It's interesting.
Click on download that.
M.
At Google.
Oh, no, that Google will.
Let me know. Mm-hmm. Let me.
Mm-hmm.
Here we are.
This looks my more like I'm 64.
This time I'll follow your instructions,
so anyone is allowed to contribute,
but today it's.
It's your fault in case.
Personally, personally,
I would have started the before
downloading and forking and opening.
I would have done.
Some code inquiry.
Straight on GitHub.
I'm already accepting.
OK.
You have to use a fork of Visual Studio
for me and so it's easy to use or to
integrate with all the extensions,
so it's a good alternative.
It's OK. I mean,
I don't have particular preferences.
I mean VS code,
I think now is 70% of development is on
VS code and from time to time there is
some fork trying to integrate things.
But at the same time, um,
VS code was a a first fork of eight
option.
Uh.
It's basically the same thing. OK,
now I have anti gravity now.
Oh.
But you can start fresh. No, no,
start fresh.
I go next.
OK.
OK now.
**** that.
Uh.
Much.
K.com.
Are so.
I should have some temp test folder.
OK, so I mean.
For the rest,
I mean it's it's fault so far,
but you can take your part of fault by
suggesting things. I mean,
I'm just following instructions so far.
At some point I may change my attitude,
but so far because the risk is that it is
just another class and I mean the.
Go today is trying to have you.
In fact, the repo is not that big. OK,
that's more. OK, now that I'm here,
anyone has an idea while waiting
anti-gravity to finish to clone the
repository? Anyone has an idea?
Of the how can I do some inspection
before downloading the full code base?
Asking the A asking the AI asking the AI
how?
Like or something.
So there are I think that there are two
approaches.
I mean basically one is somehow I fork
into some editor. No one mentioned cursor.
Cursor is another option.
Cursor is an online editor and service
with the integrated with AI that could
have been we just record code.
Integrated with compiler or with the uh
uh.
With GPT or with cloud,
I mean pretty much any vendor now gives
you integration with the IDs,
but if I want to stay just in the cloud,
I mean without going to the dev part.
I'm lazy.
That's the link of picking it up to the
chat. OK, this this was also a suggestion.
An alternative can be let's as to the
chat. OK, so first prompt prompt.
What is the prompt?
So for my assignment, sorry,
let me start the the chat outside of the
project so that no information for my.
Assignment.
Roject of Advanced Rogramming course.
Uh, I have to review the and top.
Ng codebase.
Looking for memory management style
otential.
Uh.
Issues and security related issues.
The URL of the repo is.
So in general, when you start,
it's a good idea to give your goal to the
AI,
say that that's my goal because this will
be the first thing that will be passed
into onto all the context afterwards to
the model and so you will get.
Uh, the right context.
It can be also a good idea now that I
pasted it to say OK.
OK, Google.
UniPi course catalog.
The most beautiful.
System.
OK.
It may be an option.
I can also select the English.
OK,
it may be an option also to provide the
the URL to the syllabus.
This will help the context too.
Um.
OK.
It will be.
So as you can see now the AI is
navigating. OK, notice that it.
Depending on the questions,
this way of producing the output may not
be complete in the sense that the code
base is highly.
Cross reference that piece of files. OK,
when the eye browses the web,
the general AI typically is not really so
good at.
Being exhaustive, so uh.
To some extent, in your mind,
the first question that you have to pose
yourself, perhaps even by browsing,
opening randomly files, etcetera,
is whether you think that VI may get the
relevant information by opening a few
files.
Or not,
because if you need to look at the full
code base,
perhaps whether it's VCS code or any
other editor and and fork and cloning the
repro locally may be a good idea. OK,
so I mean both are.
Uh, reasonable, OK.
Anyway,
from end tops on docs and blog C++ doing
OK control plane and UI mostly in Lua.
External libraries like and DPI,
et cetera.
Memory management styling C++ side engine
from analysis and blocks and then top and
G source manual memory management with
new.
Drive blocks ownership usually stored in
lease or array of interfaces.
Each interface owns a ocket olling thread.
And allocate spare interface.
Statistic structures.
So.
You get some suggestion in source and
include the fine classes,
call it something like network interface,
flow, etcetera.
Few more other other thing.
Look for new and include malloc, free,
etcetera. So at this level,
as you can see,
the AI is not even sure whether the
allocation is made by malloc,
new or whatever. She found some.
Some articles online describing the
implementation and that's it.
I mean we got some report and and now.
Let me zoom a little bit,
otherwise we're losing something. OK,
because now we are in advanced
programming, so I mean,
we don't like ******** and we'd like to
be really grounded to have a real.
Understanding.
So what in a memory management context,
what are the elements that are relevant
to memory management?
I mean, we said C++,
so we know that C++ is garbage collector
free as a language.
And we know that the heap memory will be
either managed explicitly.
New delete.
And in that case,
you can get inspired by Ross,
the conventions that have been boiled
down into the language. I mean,
who's responsible for allocating and
who's responsible for?
Deleting memory.
Another thing that you may ask is OK.
Maybe there is a garbage collector inside,
so I will like first to have a look into
the. Is there some garbage collector?
There are libraries. OK,
so in principle you can get garbage
collection even though C++ does not
provide.
Collection. Uh.
Or reference counting is another good
question.
Is this code base using reference
counting or not? OK,
so as you can see the questions should
come not from following advice of this
stupid thing that we call the A I.
Uh, which is very useful. Uh,
but from what you learned during the
course. So OK, what's next?
I think that uh.
Antigravity.
It's now ready.
For this.
OK.
Let's leave it here so that I propose
just to go following some order in this
exercise. The first part,
let's try to use.
The UR, the web-based, etcetera.
And then just as a second part,
let's cross-check our statements that we
possibly quickly find found.
Using the this traditional web chat style
thing,
let's double check whether the our
findings are relevant and accurate by
using anti-gravity.
So we do both our words.
Yes.
Which?
That's,
I mean this is another style which of
course it's it's it's it's possible,
but actually that is more on the software
developing side. OK, so I mean.
Of course if we but then you must be you
you first thing you should learn how to
compile the project and that's already
it's complicated in general.
I mean when you go to non trivial trivial
project the first day typically spend
just to understand and make the
development.
Development environment up and running.
OK,
so the hope when you when you bring in
the AI is that you can skip that thing
because the AI is good enough in the
analysis. But yes, you're right,
if you want to go deeper,
it's more likely that you have to go down
and do more.
Practically. Thanks. OK.
OK. So next question,
garbage collection do can now please.
From now on, use only GitHub repo,
not external.
Sources.
In general this is a good.
I mean trying to confine the the AI to
some some place may be a good idea.
And can you check whether a garbage
collector is included is used?
In the project.
So this this question is one of the
question I would expect to receive as
part of your submission was clearly is it
states.
I'm aware that a garbage collection that
may be used at the even though we are in
C++.
So whether the answer is yes or no,
it is relevant as a question because it
shows that you understand that that is an
option, OK.
Yes, you're right.
And let's see the answer because one
answer can be Oh yes,
of course in there is and then I will
reply yes, but in C++.
Or the the constriction.
I mean the I may violate your obligation.
I mean that.
OK, so solo no, no, it says.
But Lua includes a garbage collector.
So actually.
DI short answer,
there is no CC plus plus side garbage
collector in top and top PNG.
The only GC in the project is the one
provided by the embedded Lua JIT runtime.
Which man is manages to object only,
not the C++ object. So it's OK. I mean,
it's a good answer. She doesn't.
She didn't cheat. I mean,
she considered both sides of the story.
And basically we're also getting
information.
Where we can look for more information in
terms of.
OK, now I can say let's restrict to C++.
Core and can now can you now check?
Whether whether some reference counting
is used or not.
Another interesting prompt with the
output. OK,
basically in the overall understanding
this is a big statement and again there
were no mention in the output proposed by
the AI.
I tried to run it over. Yes,
and this is one of the biggest impact in
the AI of the AI in programming because
programmers tend to dislike to document
what they do.
Because they there are several way of
things. Many programmers tend to say, OK,
you know what?
We I'm writing so beautiful code which is
set explaining someone will have to read
everything and will understand and see
the light.
This is a typical attitude of a
programmer and the other thing is.
Keep inserting useless comments in the
code,
especially union programmers tend to
comment something like I iterate over the
this thing and then for each in the and
say come on,
I mean if you write for each this.
You should in typical.
Typically when you write code you should
document where,
especially where you you take decision
not to illustrate in Italian or in
English what the code does,
which typically is self-explaining.
But sometimes they say, OK,
I don't use quick sort,
let's use bubble sort.
It's good enough and not I don't expect
performances because I use the suboptimal
sorting out because I'm lazy and I don't
want to spend time to.
Implement quick sort.
I mean this this is OK because uh you you
took a design decision uh and and who's
reading the code to say uh.
Why he didn't use a quick sort OK or the
library sorting algorithm?
So these kind of things. But yes,
you're right,
one of the user that AI is finding and
one of the reason because both anthropic
and open AI are investing heavily as long
with.
Google, etc.
AI inside programming is that AI
shortened the time that someone has to
spend to understand the code base than
before by order of magnitude.
The impact is huge.
And I mean it's safe because if you make
the eye generating the code,
then you need someone checking the
generated code.
But asking question about the code base
is safe because I mean it's just reading
OK.
Short version,
I can't see any evidence of a reference
reference counting scheme in the end top
C++ core and given how the project is
written.
This is a more interesting statement.
It's very likely that they rely on manual
ownership plus containers,
not on shared pointer,
unique pointer or a custom ref count base
class.
But I also need to be honest,
this is the new flavour of GPT 5.1.
They are trying to make the ILS
sycophants a conditioner.
In in English, it's and then.
With the tool I have here,
I cannot mechanically grab the whole repo,
so I can't mathematically prove there is
0 reference counting anywhere.
This is a big improvement.
I mean a few months ago it would be, yeah,
be sure I just check it out.
So we appreciate the honesty in in the
thing and in fact also it also shows that
this a I's.
Now when they process code,
they don't fetch the full code base.
They start making grep statements on the
common line. This is also true in code.
And you see that you see bash and
everything and actually they found that
browsing the code base is best done by
the AI by selecting code and basically
using sad or grep to get the output of
portions.
Of the code that which the AI uses quite
extensively in.
In Codex,
this is performed by the Codex agent. Uh.
In the Um in Code, it is performed by the.
By the the eye itself so.
That's what.
So now let me mirror the prompts in and
let's see the differences between the two
eyes in the in the in the.
In there.
So thinking both ways, again, beware,
I have both paid versions. OK,
so when you use the free version,
the output may be less sophisticated,
which is a good thing.
So you have to use your brain instead of
picking on the eye brain only, so it's OK,
but be more suspicious if you're using
the the free version because they are
less model.
Oh, this is a a fairly so um.
You know that airplanes have two in
flight system, one is active,
the other is passive.
So that in case of and typically they
tend to have two different
implementations. OK,
this is a typical way to try.
To sort out when you can't be sure of a
code which is mission critical.
So comparing output of two different
system in general is a good idea and I
think that with AI it makes sense and
sometimes as we did.
We can ask to an AI an opinion about the
code that generated by the other AI.
This is a fairly standard approach which
is fairly intuitive.
Under the assumption that they both will
be wrong,
but hopefully on different subjects and
so we can rely on that.
Good.
I mean.
OK.
We're getting a full report.
Didn't inspect that.
Including also the vulnerabilities.
Look at.
It got.
OK, I'm impressed. Sorry.
I didn't expect such a huge it it is.
I keep changing AI so the last few months
I'm using more GPT than than cloud so.
I I miss this.
OK. Oh.
Also, also GPT wrote.
OK.
Come on, are you serious?
OK.
Beware, that's interesting. I mean,
you may feel that, oh, that's beautiful.
I'm going to use only Claude because he's
beautiful.
Let's consider that one of the thing that
we are expecting at your submission is
when you double check it. So I mean.
You can take your chance and say OK,
I spend less time in generation,
but then you will have to spend much more
time in reviewing the output. Up to you.
I'm sorry, I do respect this thing.
I was expecting more like.
Yeah, it's. I mean, I think it's.
So few other minutes and we'll get a new
version of top preview and then fix it.
It's OK.
Mm.
I think it's the first time uh I I get so
much output uh from uh.
I mean, that's impressive.
And to some extent pointless.
'Cause I mean, oh,
we also get diagrams on the layout of
data structures.
No,
the point is that now we have to take
your chance.
You trust the first output of the eye and
spend the rest of your time in double
checking every single wine that has been
generated or.
No,
actually Claude downloaded the part of a
code the the end top documentation.
I.
Here OK basically did same similar thing
as GPT. I mean it's searching for the web.
Yeah, but I'm I'm curious. I mean,
now I'm curious to see where these things
led, because actually.
Leave it. I mean,
we will come back at some point when at
some point it would.
Let's stop this thing.
Hmm.
It was the first prompt,
so he deleted everything.
So there was a uh.
It was selected the refreshments,
there's a deep thinking,
so I removed that so that hopefully.
We get a more reasonable output. I mean,
it was completely crazy.
No, now this is interesting.
Please answer your question.
I mean for Claude for GPT.
She declared that she didn't do that.
I mean she fetched a few files.
We don't know which one.
Claude is actually cloning on a terminal,
the repo to analyze the repo.
OK, now now it's.
Observation.
Man, where are you?
It's very it's getting complicated,
I mean.
I think that at school,
at high school professor,
we reading a same generated this way.
And have no way to understand it.
OK, now stop.
OK,
let's let's go and and follow the the
three lines.
So with the that's interesting with the
we close the one way GPT is clearly less.
GPT is more like can you confirm by
executing on my behalf this this this
comments. OK,
so we concluded that there are no.
No reference counting.
So memory management is managed. How?
Which are other interesting question that
we can pose related to memory management?
Let's go back to Advanced rogramming.
That's dictating.
Which which stores? No,
actually we got this answer I mean at
least to some extent and then we will ask
using the code base.
No, I mean.
I found the prompt that basically crashes
the claude. I think now it can be.
It can be.
The.
Nevertheless, it's point in general.
I mean,
I'm surprised because in general they try
to save money by outputting not too many
tokens.
So I'm impressed about how many token is
generating this thing,
and it's completely pointless.
I thought it was for the thinking,
etcetera, but I mean,
this is clearly pointless.
To the point that it is basically a bug,
I think. I can ask for a borrow check.
Borrow check. OK, question.
Is there borrow borrow checker or similar
in the repo?
It's troubles. It's costing them. No,
there is no borrow checker or anything
conceptually close to Rust ownership
borrowing model. OK, so.
We ruled out this makes sense because
Luca is older than Rust.
So I can add this is from my experience,
so I'm cheating now in C++ memory
management typically.
Often using uses patterns such as
creating reusable pool of objects so that
the memory is using reducing the heap
user.
Or fragmentation,
because if you remember one of the
problem of the malloc when we studied the
malloc is the fragmentation.
So there are several techniques in C++ to
use classes which try to reduce heap
fragmentation.
That's oh, OK.
OK.
So there is also a code we can send it to
to Luca. Luca.
Um.
Let's take some uh uh.
Memory leak. Oh, OK,
actually she read also comments in the in
the in the issues.
Let me see in the beginning.
Manual memory management with defensive
patterns.
This is the way for the labels that from
the source code analysis and this goes
back to the your colleague.
Point actually it use it.
It uses parser interface as a file source.
Observation.
No throw usage prevents exception from
location failure.
No checking pattern defensive checks
after location.
Warning logging failures are logged.
They clean up proper deleting the
structure for early,
which is a good thing because many C++
programmers forget about this.
Style assessment.
Mixed modern C with C style manual
management.
No widespread user smart pointers.
Reliance on rule pointers with minimal
lifetime management.
Defensive programming.
Allocator used the Uh JA malloc.
This is an informative.
We learned that the heap can be managed
by different allocators because you can
always allocate a chunk of memory and
manage with the different allocators all
the time.
The use of different allocators is
typically made for optimizing or
obtaining properties.
Such as that safety for some part of the
heap and more efficient approaches for
other parts of the heap.
There are several considerations,
so it's interesting that it checked about
the different malloc.
Interesting that Claude spotted this
thing and uh uh.
Opening I did not.
And then Lua is an issue. Let's keep.
Uh.
Security related concern,
allocation failure,
handling vulnerability patterns.
New pointer the reference in potential.
This is I think for any C++ code,
so this is not and the final behaviour if
pointer is used without rechecking.
Also this is a general.
So no real.
OK, let's ask do.
Uh, you find multiple heaps or allocators.
In the meantime.
Let's do.
I I.
Added a new system to my my PC,
so let's try to use it.
So there was the comment about JA Malloc.
O Let's try to.
Um.
Oh, you said the.
So now.
I'm using antigravity.
Now let's see whether this works or not.
This has finished.
From what I can see,
there's no sign of multiple independent
tips allocator being used inside C++ core.
More precisely,
the C++ code in the top PNG is written in
the usual style that assumes a single
process wide allocator new delete malloc
free STL containers.
From GitHub issues,
you do see that some builds are packaged.
On that means the whole process is linked
against JM unlock on that platform,
not is dead.
This is basically saying Claude I I I
you're say you you're you're telling a a
false thing and a full story because
basically Claude told me that the project
is using JE Malloc and and.
Uh, GPT says no.
I mean there is some mention.
So.
OK,
the best thing you should like this anti
gravity don't tell.
Then it will actually.
Yeah, you're right. OK.
But now I think we can conclude that that
this is a.
A sensible thing to do,
but now you see the difference between
the various systems. OK,
so Claude basically said oh don't worry,
but it was sensible and say the
allocation is patterns have been derived
from this particular file.
GPT didn't tell us which files were used
to derive conclusions,
but from the trace of the the the
thinking I've got that GPT is aware that
she only browse needs to browse GitHub.
So I'm pretty sure that at least either
is the documentation or the issue,
but only.
It up.
At the same time, GPT says OK,
can you check on my behalf by running
grep?
So that you can check because.
Yes, and as your colleague was not sorry.
No, sorry.
OK.
So there is a a mention in the configure
AC and in the read me for compilation.
So from.
I should probably spend some some time on
on this,
but nevertheless apparently it GPT was
right.
Jemalloc is referenced and is on all only
used for Lua I will add.
I mean,
it's a dependency that is coming from Lua,
OK.
Oh,
this is the trace of the so actually
still working.
We'll have to wait for the the output. OK,
let's.
For the moment,
let's keep exploring why waiting the
analysis of course of the code.
By the way,
there's no nothing wrong in say. OK,
let me go on GitHub and search.
Inside the let me go even in the source
so I'm sure that in a source and I can
say J e-mail look.
By the way,
graph beats AI 4 to 0 in this kind of
task, OK.
This is an interesting fact to report in
How did I verify the statement?
I did the graph.
There is no reference to the JE malloc
other than in Lua,
so we can basically conclude that the C++
is not using JE malloc.
OK.
By the way, as I was saying, I I won't.
Pretend that this is the best question I
will pose myself during the project.
Please try to validate high level
statements such as I mean the style so we
don't have.
Uh.
So um.
Um.
Who is responsible for the allocating the
the memory allocated with new?
This is a reasonable question, OK.
Which refers to.
The C++ code that owns the pointer is
responsible.
So basically.
The container acts basically as the roots
of a manually developed memory strategy,
but basically you can think them as of
the roots where the system when will
delete the container will delete also.
Hierarchically so.
Look at this. That, by the way,
would have been my next question to the
eye.
When you deal with programming languages
such as C++ and C++,
because I mean there are not many,
but I mean programming languages object
oriented with destructors.
It's a good question to ask yourself what
is the role of the destructor,
especially memory.
Management destructor may play a
significant role, OK,
and we just get the confirmation that
basically destructors are responsible for
the allocating data structures, OK.
So we are working with network and the
system is meant to analyse the network,
so I would expect a little bit of string
management.
What are the question you will ask for
string management?
The technology behind it maybe.
So first of all,
why string management is worth?
Honestly, uh.
I was expecting more from.
Yeah, I mean.
This way, 10 days will not be enough. OK,
but I mean, is yeah, I mean, it's OK.
So this is an open game.
Everyone can pick up. I'm trying to.
Showcase everything. OK, so strings.
Why strings are so important?
They may fragment heap and um the they
may. If you go the Java way,
it can lead to a lot of copy buffer
copying.
So string management is crucial because.
It may affect performances and in
software like Ntop,
performance is rather important because
you are trying to monitor fast pace.
Elements,
especially now that networking is 100
gigabit per second. OK,
and so you're you're going so for 400
gigabit per second, so.
The speed,
the the the speed of the network is such
that the processing speed of the CPU and
efficiency of the algorithms may affect
your ability to do real time or not
analysis. OK, OK.
OK.
Yes,
but that I will say that if you are at
the pocket level,
you even get just the bytes.
But typically these these tools typically
have.
I mean if you are the network admin and
you want to look,
you're looking for something,
typically you want to do search,
so that's strings.
So these kind of tools have to to
generate strings.
The problem it it's from maybe is less
important for the control the. Oh no, no,
definitely.
But our question is what is the style so
that we can judge whether it is OK or not.
So what is the string manipulation?
Style in the code base.
Actually yeah, yeah,
I was saying I did digress.
I should stick on the GitHub,
but the user told me that the GitHub is
the source.
Uh,
I love to to read the comments from the
AI 'cause sometimes they're so fun.
OK.
As an optional drop in replacement for
the standard memory allocator to optimize
memory usage and reduce fermentation.
And it is basically a configuration part
because Jemalloc then simply redefine
malloc and so during the linking of the
project will inherit the malloc
implementation from Gemalloc. So OK,
this is a nice answer.
This has been produced by.
Actually reading the full code base it
took longer.
We learn something also from this.
Maybe the first analysis is convenient to
produce it using the standard web
interface etc.
And then when you wanna cross check on go
deep.
Then or to be to get a comprehensive
answer that regards all the code base
rather than just you know overall and
overall properties then using an additor
locally.
They gets you better results. OK,
so I mean.
OK, C++ core.
They use a very traditional mixed CC plus
plus string style,
so char start fixed buffers.
This is in in the traditional networking
also because packets have a fixed length,
so typically.
Chart star is a typical way to to deal
with them and as the SM print F or
similar Sync is used but mostly as a
convenience wrapper at a higher level,
not as a strict policy.
So this means that basically is C.
Style buffer style string processing at
the core.
No sign of modern stuff such as a string
view format, safe string abstractions. OK,
so personally I will share this,
but I mean now I'm I'm cheating because I
know Luca.
And I'm pretty sure that Luca is a C fan
basically and so I'm pretty sure that he
use it as the core,
the C and then the object orientation. OK,
so we are left with little time and few
other questions first.
Uh, even the styles.
So now let me pose the question to the
local.
No to the local chat.
Dismiss. There we are.
Can you validate the security?
Can you find the security related the
weaknesses in?
The C++ code base.
OK, this is.
Unless.
It was the same question.
To the AI so that we can.
So that's interesting, I mean because.
Um.
The buffer overflow.
So how do you check before asking the AI,
how would you check the potential buffer
overflows in a code base?
So.
Oh yeah, I mean you can use tools,
but I mean if suppose we are,
we go back 20 years,
no tools because I mean the tools
basically embeds the behaviour.
No, no, even without the eye.
I mean let let's stick to the core
programming programming that live live in
us.
I mean what are the so the because buffer
overflow is often misused as I mean it's
considered.
A bad thing in general,
but I mean where where would you look?
If you only have notepad,
where would you look for buffer or flows?
But we are in C,
so basically everything is unsafe or C++.
Said like a string copy function by which
will use the string and copy that that I
mean that that is and in fact it was
mentioned in the the and copy function
typically.
So the invocation of a function that.
Performs boundary checks on on a pointer.
Basically that that that it is.
But the first thing that you have to
check in general is the automatic
allocated memory. So if you want to focus.
In in the.
In the in in the search for a buffer
overflow,
first you will concentrate on stack
allocated memory because the the essence
of the stack overflow attacker is to be
able to.
Use one of these function that don't
check the boundaries.
So of course your colleague is right that
that's important,
but the I will focus on the static.
No, sorry,
not static on on on the on the stack
because the essence of the stack overflow,
so sorry, buffer overflow,
it was exploiting the the absence of
boundary checks.
To override the stack because it's where
you can get the best out of it,
especially if the the you are calling a
library which elevated the privilege to
administrative and you can.
Rewrite the return address in the
activation record so that you can get my
first buffer overflow.
I think it was 97 or 6 and I managed to
get a beautiful bash prompt route.
By exploiting one of this thing and and
the core was basically not only the fact
that you you buffer overflow,
but you have to understand the the layout
of the memory so that you can write your
interesting stuff and the 1st place I
will look for will be stack.
Not heap.
Of course in the heap you can do,
but it's more difficult to produce damage
in the heap rather than in the stack,
because the heap depends on how the
project has been developed.
The stack behaves in a well understood
way with activation records,
so there you can get.
Uh, much more interesting stuff. OK, so.
There are several security relevant risk
pattern. Luca, you're in trouble.
We'll send you a report,
but with the access I have,
I can't do a complete audit and this is
OK.
Uh.
OK, a lot of excusation. I'm sorry,
I can't do this. So I mean,
I can give you an opinion.
Um.
Huh.
Truncation.
Plus so string copy is used the.
The destination is not null terminated
because in C the the tradition is to null
terminate strings.
So I mean with truncation you can you you
you protect the buffer,
but basically you can get an inconsistent
string. This is.
Uh, the.
Uh.
General. So in from this shallow analysis,
nothing that isn't.
I mean all these things are if you use C
string styles, basically that's the.
Um.
From source network interface C.
Uh,
you can see the typical pattern on hand
rolled protocol parsing.
They do some blank checker before the NS
header, which is good,
but all bounds checking is manual,
so error prone because of the programmer.
A complex protocol logic security input.
And top NG often runs as a root or
elevated user. OK,
so basically nothing new.
Good news for Luca. I mean,
there are no obvious problems. OK,
let's see if antigravity.
Yeah.
Hmm.
Identify multiple.
I mean this is part of reasoning,
so it's not the.
I mean you can get multiple main copy
calls, most appears safe,
but investigating 2 specific instances in
utils CPP for potential buffer overflows.
OK, I mean.
Overall, I I like it there here.
I think it's close to wrap up.
So uh.
While I try to wrap up the whole session,
let's leave the the the code to run.
So what are our takeaways?
So as you can see we use it basically
three AIS Cloud.
We generated probably the most useless
output, 2 verbose,
too big to cross-check and with I won't
say hallucination,
but it pointed out not so relevant things,
OK.
I would have expected.
I mean you can ask when I I paste in the
first prompt from GPT.
If I were using Cloud,
I would probably have stopped it and
corrected the prompter by saying but
don't do a full analysis,
I will ask you for specific things. OK,
so that you can go incremental.
So first factor.
When you use the AI,
please do it this way.
Do it incremental so that it's easy also
to cross check and validate the
statements,
because otherwise the risk is that you
spend a lot of time.
If you use the free version,
you may even run out of tokens before you
have an answer.
And do cross checking between different
AI's is a good thing.
For a general overview of code base and
repositories you can use the general web
even.
Without restricting to GitHub, I mean,
but also let the AI find articles that
explains the code base.
I think it's a good thing,
but then you go and cross-check every
statement so that you you see that there
are no.
Misunderstandings,
but as your colleagues was suggesting,
eventually I totally agree that using
cloning the repo on your machine.
And doing some check about the statement
is necessary because as you've seen the A
I cherry pick some files from the repo
and try tries to draw conclusions.
In some cases I felt OK with memory
management.
Because memory managing is so widely
available in all the source code that I'm
pretty sure that any file you pick up you
will find the same pattern.
So I mean I felt safe to continue using
the online version if we decided for more
vertical properties.
May not be the best thing.
Global properties such as security that
is requires browsing the full repo,
so I will use some local tool and not I
won't trust too much the the online
version.
Uh.
Submission.
I would have appreciated to receive the
output,
which probably is cut and paste of the
most relevant consideration you got from
the chat.
You can even at some point can you
produce me a summary about the garbage
collection?
Can you give me a summary about reference
counting and copy paste so you get a nice
report and as a separate document those
were the questions and in this in this in
this case basically they revolve around
the notion of memory.
Management. I mean,
if you understand the memory management.
Those were the interesting questions.
I could have posed other questions that I
think are interesting.
Um.
Is this code base using multiple
inheritance?
That would have been a pro question.
Why this would have been a a question?
Oh, it works. I mean,
but it's error prone and basically
depending on the flavor,
whether it is virtual multiple
inheritance or non virtual multiple
inheritance,
you may have a single copy or dual copy
of the inheritance.
Base class OK that the the diamond
problem that at some point Andrea pointed
out OK and so this may relate to the
memory because you may have copies of the
memory and or not.
What?
Google finished. Are you sure?
OK,
C++ found weak random number generation,
high severity.
In general this is a good concern. Oh,
potential buffer overflow in string
replacement.
Utility CPP.
It performs a a movie and a copy assuming
the destination buffer is large enough.
This is a significant.
Recommendation Fixed sites, password,
buffer. This is another.
OK,
so I mean it's pretty good as a report.
I wouldn't expect the big security issues
in in this code base. So I mean,
but as you can see,
even the output feels more like, OK,
you read the code, you give me an opinion.
Thank you and then.
If I want to check whether this I I can
go to UTCPP line at this line and check
with my eyes what the code look like and
then say OK I check it and she's right or
no.
It's clearly there are a few lines that
ensures that this is safe.
OK in this in this case I I think this is
a post positive.
I mean I I'm pretty sure that if I go to
Uthil's CPP at this line I will find the
code that that I mean.
Otis is the typical file where you put
the functions that you use the most. OK,
and so that there is a buffer overflow
there I really doubt.
So this is a good example of.
Where, uh,
let let me go and check because I can see
that the machine don't sees the
assumptions or the full assumptions,
but it is like it's unlikely that that's,
uh, buffer overflow.
I will expect so. OK, so I thank you.
And so at the end basically questions one
file output and verification which
includes I code the repository,
I use an anti gravity or Visual Studio
code with ChatGPT or with the free
version of Copilot.
Whatever and I got this report and I
checked it in the code and from the
snippet it looks like it's OK,
that's fine. OK,
the way you double check it that the
output was not only correct but also
relevant because the GEMA lock was
correct.
The end of the day. But was it relevant?
No, it was just a Lincoln thing.
OK.
Thank you. See you. Oh,
so see you tomorrow.
And this is the before last class because
next week Monday is holiday.
Wednesday is I'm in London and
unfortunately the plane lands too late.
And anyway,
I think we did enough in the course.
Yesterday I spoke with Professor
Corradini. We agreed that we tortured.
With you and not to spend the last two
classes in keeping making exercise,
having discussions,
answering to questions,
probably I will say on Thursday we will
publish.